# António Miguel de Jesus Domingues

[GENOMICS] DATA ANALYST · MULTI-OMICS

Schubertstrasse 31, 01307 Dresden, Germany

□ (+49) 01575-1976556 | ■ amjdomingues@gmail.com | # http://adomingues.github.io/ | • adomingues | • antonio-domingues

## Summary\_

Bioinformatician with more than 10 years experience in the analysis and integration of multi-omics datasets and a background in experimental biology. I enjoy experimenting with data visualization to communicate results effectively, and to automate data processes to deliver insights more efficiently. More recently, I have been dipping my toes in machine learning, and leading projects at the interface of biology, data science and software development.

## Skills

**Core competencies** Genomic data analysis, RNA-seq, small RNA-seq, ATAC-seq, Exosome sequencing, NGS

R/Bioconductor, bash, Python, bpipe (workflow manager), git, Cluster computing (LSF / SLURM), Markdown, LaTeX, statistics, AWS

Programming Machine Learning

**Operating systems** Linux Ubuntu, Windows, MacOS

**Laboratory** Cell culture, RNA extraction, DNA cloning, qPCR, animal tissue extraction, single-cell calcium imaging, FACS

**Languages** Portuguese (Native speaker), English (Fluent), German (Conversational), French

## Education

University of Leicester

Leicester, United Kingdom

PhD in Cell Physiology and Pharmacology

2006 - 2009

• Thesis title: Cloning and characterization of novel NMDA receptors splice variants in Glia

University of Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

MSc in Molecular Microbiology

2002 - 2005

- Thesis title: The role of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunits in Aß induced toxicity
- Host institution: Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology (CNC), Coimbra, Portugal

University of Aveiro Aveiro Aveiro, Portugal

BSC IN BIOLOGY 1997 - 2001

- Semester project 1: Phytochelatin synthesis in Pisum sativum L. induced by zinc.
- Semester project 2: Identification of proteins that interact with protein phosphatase type 1 gamma subunit using the yeast two-hybrid approach.

# Work Experience

### **Dewpoint Therapeutics GmbH**

Dresden, Germany

ASSOCIATE PRINCIPAL SCIENTIST (DATA SCIENCE)

March 2022 - Present

- Lead the development of a Shiny application from requirements to CI/CD deployment in AWS with a team of DevOps and software developers.
- Biomarker discovery to drive R&D programs using conventional differential gene expression analysis and network based approaches.
- Evaluation of CROs for sequencing services.
- Prototyped explainable machine learning models for molecule prioritization.
- Evaluation and recommendation of Data Science products and Services.
- Supervision of a Data Science intern.
- Lead projects executed by external contractors.

SENIOR SCIENTIST (DATA SCIENCE) January 2021 - Present

- · Custom analysis of genomic data.
- Differential gene expression analysis for multiple disease programs (RNA-seq data).
- Development of proof of concept Shiny applications.
- Design RNA-seq experiments with R&D teams and liase with external CROs for their execution.
- · Design and implementation of ETL pipelines.
- Development of an internal R package for the analysis of mass-spectrometry measurements.
- · Prototyping of machine learning models.
- Leading several projects to set-up Data Science infrastructure in AWS (NF-Tower, Shiny server)
- Design of data ontologies for storage sample metadata.
- Evaluation and recommendation of Data Science products and Services.
- Supervision of a Data Science intern.
- Lead projects executed by external contractors.

#### Scientific Computing Facility (Scionics GmbH), MPI-CBG

Dresden, Germany

June 2019 - December 2020

**BIOINFORMATICS DATA ANALYST** 

- · Custom analysis of genomic data.
- Integration of multi-omics data (Ribo-Seq and RNA-seq datasets).
- Pipeline development for mass-spectrometry data.
- Pipeline development for long read sequencing (PacBio) to detect genomic insertions.
- Differential gene expression analysis (RNA-seq data).
- Teaching of a data analysis and visualization course (R) highly rated by students.
- Implementation of conda environments in production to increase reproducibility of data analysis.

#### **Institute of Molecular Biology**

Mainz, Germany

Dec. 2014 - May 2019

- POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER / BIOINFORMATICIAN
- Developed and implemented pipelines for small RNA analysis (piRNA, miRNA).
- Integrated and analyzed multiple -omics datasets (smRNA-seq, mRNA-seq, total RNA-seq, ATAC-seq).
- Developed scripts and tools for custom sequencing data analysis.
- Designed and advised on the design of figures and best visualization practices.
- Tested the suitability of new library preparation kits / methods for next-generation sequencing.
- · Coordinated the installation of a Zebrafish Facility Management database. I ensured good communication between the IT support, the fish facility manager and the database developer.
- Internal group teaching of UNIX command-line usage and bash.

#### **Biotechnology Center TUD (Biotec)**

Dresden, Germany

Oct. 2013 - Nov. 2014

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER / BIOINFORMATICIAN

- Built a pipeline for variant calling from exome sequencing data.
- Troubleshooting of sequencing issues.
- Advised users on NGS experimental design.
- Liaised with clinical staff and organized the collection and processing of clinical samples.
- Analysis of chromatin associated proteins (DamID-seq and ChIP-seq)
- Differential gene expression (RNA-seq data).
- · T-cell receptor profiling.

#### Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics (MPI-CBG)

Dresden, Germany

Oct. 2009 - Aug. 2013

- MARIE CURIE POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW
- Created new stable cell lines with tagged RNA-binding proteins.
- Prepared RNA samples for splice-junction arrays, RNA-seq and ChIP-seq.
- · Analyzed the data of all experiments of my project.
- · Collaborated with students and Postdoctoral researchers in conceiving and analyzing experiments.
- · Trained doctoral students.

#### **Center for Neuroscience and Cell Biology**

Coimbra, Portugal

May 2005 - Jan. 2006

CELL CULTURE TECHNICIAN

- · Maintained mammalian cell lines and plated them for experiments according the requests of users.
- Ordering and budgeting of cell culture reagents
- Preparation of cell culture media.
- Teaching aseptic cell culture techniques and best practices to students.

# Open source contributions \_\_\_\_\_

#### Package maintainer

May. 2020 - Present

Bioconductor

- Fixed bugs to keep the package as part of Biocondutor.
- · User support.

GENEOVERLAP

# **Teaching and mentoring**

**Dewpoint Therapeutics** Dresden, Germany

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN

Supervised an undergraduate student developing machine learning models.

· Fully remote supervision.

IMB alumni Dresden, Germany

IMB MENTORING PROGRAM

· Mentoring of a PhD student at one of my former places of employment.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

DATA ANALYSIS AND VISUALIZATION WITH R

• Taught data manipulation (dplyr) and visualization (ggplot2).

• Students ranked the course very good or excellent in a survey.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

ALTERNATIVE SPLICING

· Pre-doc practical course.

Taught chromatin imunnoprecipitation and 3'RACE.

Supervised the students as they carried out the experiments.

Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics

CHROMATIN IP AND RNA LOCALIZATION

· Pre-doc practical course.

• Taught primer design and qPCR.

• supervised the students whilst they carried out the experiments.

University of Leicester

LABORATORY SUPERVISION AND MENTORING OF A MEDICAL BSc STUDENT

· Taught molecular biology techniques.

Designed experiments and supervised daily work.

• For his project the student received a BSc Honours Degree.

University of Leicester

KEY SKILLS IN SCIENTIFIC WRITING AND PRESENTATION (MB1002)

Pre-doc practical course.

Advising 1st year BSc students on scientific communication.

Marking essays/presentations.

**University of Coimbra** Coimbra, Portugal

BASIC RESEARCH SKILLS TO MEDICAL STUDENTS

· Semester long research project.

- · Introduced Medical students to cell biology techniques.
- · Supervised benchwork.

# **Grants, Honors & Awards**

INTERNATIONAL

2011 - 2013 Marie Curie Intra-European fellowship for career development, FP7, U.E.

Training program in molecular neuroscience scholarship, Prodep III, U.E.

Advanced courses & workshops.

2018 CSAMA 2018: Statistical Data Analysis for Genome Scale Biology, practical course

2012

2012

2021

2021 - present

Dresden, Germany

Dresden, Germany

Dresden, Germany

2011

Leicester, United Kingdom

2006 - 2007

Leicester, United Kingdom

2006 - 2007

Desdren, Germany

Coimbra Portugal

Brixen, Italy. 2016 Project management workshop, Two day workshop Mainz, Germany. 2013 Programming for Evolutionary Biology, Two weeks, intensive Practical course Leipzig, Germany. "Software Carpentry", practical course 2013 Freising, Germany. 2012 Introduction to Biopython, practical course Leuven, Belgium. Hinxton, United Advanced RNA-Seq and ChiP-Seq Data Analysis, practical course 2012 Kingdom.

Principles of Light Microscopy, practical course Desdren Germany. Pieces & parts: a primer on brain dissection from discrete regions to micronuclei, practical course Aveiro, Portugal.

# **Publications & presentations**

Asterisk (\*) denotes equal contribution of the first two authors.

#### PEER-REVIEWED PAPERS

The RNA binding protein human antigen R is a gatekeeper of liver homeostasis

Subramanian, P., S. Gargani, A. Palladini, M. Chatzimike, M. Grzybek, M. Peitzsch, A. D. Papanastasiou, I. Pyrina, V. Ntafis, B. Gercken, M. Lesche, A. Petzold, A. Sinha, M. Nati, V. R. Thangapandi, I. Kourtzelis, M. Andreadou, A. Witt, A. Dahl, R. Burkhardt, R. Haase, **A. M. d. J. Domingues**, I. Henry, N. Zamboni, P. Mirtschink, K.-J. Chung, J. Hampe, Ü. Coskun, D. L. Kontoyiannis, and T. Chavakis *Hepatology* ()

Exosomal miRNAs from Prostate Cancer Impair Osteoblast Function in Mice

Furesi, G., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, D. Alexopoulou, A. Dahl, M. Hackl, J. R. Schmidt, S. Kalkhof, T. Kurth, H. Taipaleenmäki, S. Conrad, C. Hofbauer, M. Rauner, and L. C. Hofbauer

International Journal of Molecular Sciences 23.3 p. 1285. 2022

Membrane-associated cytoplasmic granules carrying the Argonaute protein WAGO-3 enable paternal epigenetic inheritance in Caenorhabditis elegans

Schreier, J., S. Dietz, M. Boermel, V. Oorschot, A.-S. Seistrup, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, A. W. Bronkhorst, D. A. H. Nguyen, S. Phillis, E. J. Gleason, S. W. L'Hernault, C. M. Phillips, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

Nature Cell Biology pp. 1–13. 2022

Intrinsically disordered protein PID-2 modulates Z granules and is required for heritable piRNA-induced silencing in the Caenorhabditis elegans embryo

Placentino, M., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, J. Schreier, S. Dietz, S. Hellmann, B. F. de Albuquerque, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting *The EMBO Journal* 40.3 e105280. 2021

\* Extensive nuclear gyration and pervasive non-genic transcription during primordial germ cell development in zebrafish Redl, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, E. Caspani, S. Möckel, W. Salvenmoser, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting Development 148.2 dev193060. 2021

Bardet-Biedl syndrome proteins modulate the release of bioactive extracellular vesicles

Volz, A.-K., A. Frei, V. Kretschmer, A. M. de Jesus Domingues, R. F. Ketting, M. Ueffing, K. Boldt, E.-M. Krämer-Albers, and H. L. May-Simera *Nature Communications* 12.1 p. 5671. 2021

Condensation of Ded1p Promotes a Translational Switch from Housekeeping to Stress Protein Production

Iserman, C., C. D. Altamirano, C. Jegers, U. Friedrich, T. Zarin, A. W. Fritsch, M. Mittasch, **A. Domingues**, L. Hersemann, M. Jahnel, D. Richter, U.-P. Guenther, M. W. Hentze, A. M. Moses, A. A. Hyman, G. Kramer, M. Kreysing, T. M. Franzmann, and S. Alberti *Cell* 181.4 pp. 818–831. 2020

Innate Immune Training of Granulopoiesis Promotes Anti-tumor Activity

Kalafati, L., I. Kourtzelis, J. Schulte-Schrepping, X. Li, A. Hatzioannou, T. Grinenko, E. Hagag, A. Sinha, C. Has, S. Dietz, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, M. Nati, S. Sormendi, A. Neuwirth, A. Chatzigeorgiou, A. Ziogas, M. Lesche, A. Dahl, I. Henry, P. Subramanian, B. Wielockx, P. Murray, P. Mirtschink, K.-J. Chung, J. L. Schultze, M. G. Netea, G. Hajishengallis, P. Verginis, I. Mitroulis, and T. Chavakis *Cell* 183.3 771–785.e12. 2020

\* Maternal and zygotic gene regulatory effects of endogenous RNAi pathways

Almeida, M. V., A. M. d. J. Domingues, and R. F. Ketting

PLOS Genetics 15.2 e1007784. 2019

\* RppH can faithfully replace TAP to allow cloning of 5'-triphosphate carrying small RNAs Almeida, M. V., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, H. Lukas, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting Methods X 2019

PETISCO is a novel protein complex required for 21U RNA biogenesis and embryonic viability

Rodrigues, R. J. C., A. M. d. J. Domingues, S. Hellmann, S. Dietz, B. F. M. d. Albuquerque, C. Renz, H. D. Ulrich, P. Sarkies, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

Genes & Development 33.13-14 pp. 857-870. 2019

Tdrd6a Regulates the Aggregation of Buc into Functional Subcellular Compartments that Drive Germ Cell Specification

Roovers, E. F., L. J. T. Kaaij, S. Redl, A. W. Bronkhorst, K. Wiebrands, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, H.-Y. Huang, C.-T. Han, S. Riemer, R. Dosch, W. Salvenmoser, D. Grün, F. Butter, A. van Oudenaarden, and R. F. Ketting

Developmental Cell 46.3 285-301.e9. 2018

Characterization of genetic loss-of-function of Fus in zebrafish

Clinical & Experimental Immunology 184.3 pp. 389-402. 2016

Lebedeva, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, F. Butter, and R. F. Ketting

RNA Biology 14.1 pp. 29-35. 2017

Enhancers reside in a unique epigenetic environment during early zebrafish development

Kaaij, L. J. T., M. Mokry, M. Zhou, M. Musheev, G. Geeven, A. S. J. Melquiond, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, W. de Laat, C. Niehrs, A. D. Smith, and R. F. Ketting

Genome Biology 17 p. 146. 2016

Abundant cytomegalovirus (CMV) reactive clonotypes in the CD8+ T cell receptor alpha repertoire following allogeneic transplantation Link, C. S., A. Eugster, F. Heidenreich, E. Rücker-Braun, M. Schmiedgen, U. Oelschlägel, D. Kühn, S. Dietz, Y. Fuchs, A. Dahl, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, C. Klesse, M. Schmitz, G. Ehninger, M. Bornhäuser, J. Schetelig, and E. Bonifacio

SR proteins are NXF1 adaptors that link alternative RNA processing to mRNA export

Müller-McNicoll, M., V. Botti, **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, H. Brandl, O. D. Schwich, M. C. Steiner, T. Curk, I. Poser, K. Zarnack, and K. M. Neugebauer

Genes & Development 30.5 pp. 553-566. 2016

 $\label{tox:constraint} Tox: a \ multifunctional \ transcription \ factor \ and \ novel \ regulator \ of \ mammalian \ corticogenesis$ 

Artegiani, B., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, S. B. Alonso, E. Brandl, S. Massalini, A. Dahl, and F. Calegari

The EMBO Journal 34.7 pp. 896-910. 2015

Identification of four functional NR3B isoforms in developing white matter reveals unexpected diversity among glutamate receptors.

**Domingues**, **A. M. d. J.**, K. M. Neugebauer, and R. Fern

Journal of neurochemistry 117.3 pp. 449-60. 2011

Toxicity of beta-amyloid in HEK293 cells expressing NR1/NR2A or NR1/NR2B N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor subunits.

Domingues, A., S. Almeida, E. F. da Cruz e Silva, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Neurochemistry international 50.6 pp. 872-80. 2007

FK506 prevents mitochondrial-dependent apoptotic cell death induced by 3-nitropropionic acid in rat primary cortical cultures.

Almeida, S., A. M. de Jesus Domingues, L. Rodrigues, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

Neurobiology of disease 17.3 pp. 435-44. 2004

#### PREPRINTS & OTHERS

Extensive nuclear gyration and pervasive non-genic transcription during primordial germ cell development in zebrafish Redl, S., **A. M.** de **Jesus Domingues**, S. Möckel, W. Salvenmoser, M. Mendez-Lago, and R. F. Ketting *bioRxiv* p. 2020.01.10.901306. 2020

Identification of Tox chromatin binding properties and downstream targets by DamID-Seq

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, B. Artegiani, A. Dahl, and F. Calegari

Genomics Data 7 pp. 264-268. 2016

#### **REVIEWS**

\* White matter synapses: form, function, and dysfunction.

Alix, J. J. P. and A. M. de Jesus Domingues

Neurology 76.4 pp. 397-404. 2011

Glia as transmitter sources and sensors in health and disease.

Domingues, A. M. d. J., M. Taylor, and R. Fern

Neurochemistry international 57.4 pp. 359-66. 2010

#### **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

Expression of NR1/NR2B N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors enhances heroin toxicity in HEK293 cells. **Domingues, A.,** T. Cunha Oliveira, M. L. N. Laço, T. R. A. Macedo, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego *Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences* 1074 pp. 458–65. 2006

#### **ORAL PRESENTATIONS**

A family portrait: global effects of SR protein depletion on alternative splicing **Jesus Domingues**, **A. M.** de, M. Müller-McNicoll, M.-L. Ankö, and K. M. Neugebauer 8th Special Interest Group meeting on Alternative Splicing, 2011, Viena, Austria

NMDA Receptor Subunit composition Influences AßToxicity

**Domingues**, A., E. F. da Cruz e Silva, C. R. Oliveira, and A. C. Rego

34th Meeting of the Portuguese Pharmacology Society, 2003, Coimbra, Portugal

#### **SELECTED POSTER PRESENTATIONS**

\* Activation of the genome in germ cells in relation to transposon silencing and the piRNA pathway **Jesus Domingues**, **A. M.** de, S. Redl, E. Caspani, H. Dill, and R. F. Ketting *Mobile Genetic Elements and Genome Plasticity*, 2018, Santa Fé, NM, USA

Regulation of gene expression by SR proteins: a comprehensive study

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. Müller-McNicoll, and K. M. Neugebauer

Special Interest Group meeting on Integrative RNA Biology (AS-SIG), 2013, Berlin, Germany

Characterization of novel NMDA receptor subtypes

Jesus Domingues, A. M. de, M. G. Salter, and R. Fern

Society for Neuroscience, 2008, Washington, USA

## References\_

Ian Henry, PhD Rene Ketting, PhD

Head of Scientific Computing, MPI-CBG, Dresden. dr.ian.henry@gmail.com Scientific Director, IMB, Mainz (JGU). +49 6131 39 21470 / r.ketting@imb-mainz.de

Professor of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry and of Cell Biology, Yale University. + 1 203 785 3322 /

Karla M. Neugebauer, PhD

karla.neugebauer@yale.edu